All right. In this video, we're going to
talk about the different types of data
types, or at least four of them. Um, if
you remember back to the video where I
talked about variables, I described two
differentiz boxes, a small box and a
large box. That is because different
variables that are holding different
types of information use differentized
boxes.
So, when we create a variable, I have
cleared out everything in my script tag
from the last video. When we create a
variable, we use the keyword let. So
we'll say let and then we can create a
variable. We want to label it. So we're
going to give it a name and I'll say
first name
and then I put double quotes here. Or I
could put single quotes here. When I do
that, JavaScript now knows that this
type of variable is a string. A string
takes up a decent size space. So it's
going to create a larger box that's
ready to hold a string. So I could say
let first name equal TOA. Anything that
is text on your page that you're going
anytime you're storing text that has
letters or special characters that is a
string. And so the way you create a
string is you use either single quotes
or double quotes.
Um and you can create your string. We'll
talk more about strings in a future
video, but I'm going to say a string is
a data type that stores text and is
created using single or double quotes.
Okay.
And I actually want this comment to be
on the line above. So, what I'm going to
do is I'm going to highlight and I'm
going to hold the shift key and the
arrow key to highlight what I want to
move. Hit command X or controlX on a
Windows and then paste it on the next
line. So, a string is a data type that
stores text. The next type of data type
is an integer.
And an integer is a data type that
stores numbers, specifically whole
numbers.
So if I want to create an integer, I use
the keyword let. That allocates the box
in memory. I'm going to say age and that
stores an age. And then I could say 200.
And that would store the integer 200 in
a variable called age. I um because it
is an integer it stores any whole
number. Um so we could do 200 or we
could do -200 and in both cases because
it is a whole number it is an integer.
The another type of number that we can
store is a number that has a decimal
place and that is stored in a different
type of data type. So we're going to
create a comment here. I used command
slash this time and I'm going to say a
float
is a data type that
stores
decimal
numbers. So I could say let pi equal
3.14159.
And just like with an integer it stores
numbers with a decimal place and it
stores positive and negative numbers. So
if I put -3.14159,
that would be a float. Some important
things I want to point out here. The age
does not have quotes around it. Only the
string has quotes around it. The age,
um, JavaScript figures out it's a number
and then it figures out it's a whole
number and it's not in quotes, so then
it creates an integer storage place for
it. for pi. It looks at it and realizes
there's a decimal place in it and it's
not in quotation marks. So then it
creates a float storage space for that.
The last one that we're going to talk
about in this video is a boolean.
A boolean is a data type that stores
true
or false. So there's only two pieces of
information you can store in a boolean.
It's either true or it's false. So I
could say let happy today equal true
and then I'll put a semicolon. So true
is a keyword and it must be all
lowercase. In a previous video you saw
that I made the mistake of using it
uppercase. That was because I've been
programming in a different language. In
JavaScript true is a keyword and it is
all lowercase. The other option is false
which is all lowercase. And you'll
notice it turns blue. So, no quotation
marks, all lowercase. And so, happy
today is a boolean because there are no
quotes around this and it is all
lowercase and it is the keyword false.
Um, in this case, I am happy today. So,
I'm going to set it to true and that
will end this video.